A Guide to the Alexander McNutt Glasgow Family Papers, 1823-1903
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Alexander McNutt Glasgow Family Papers, 1823-1903
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1989-010
0.7 cu. ft. 2 boxes
Correspondence and financial/ legal papers of the Alexander McNutt Glasgow family of Rockbridge County, Virginia.
Glasgow family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Alexander McNutt Glasgow Family Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 1989.
Biographical Note
Alexander McNutt Glasgow, son of John and Martha ("Patsy") McNutt Glasgow (1798-1866), was born five miles from Lexington (Rockbridge County), Virginia, on October 24, 1820. He earned bachelor of arts (1842) and bachelor of law degrees from Washington College (now Washington and Lee University) and would continue to live at "Tuscan Villa," the Glasgow family's Rockbridge County home, for the remainder of his life. He farmed (tobacco and grains), operated a general mercantile business, and served as a judge in the county court and as an elder in the local Presbyterian church. Records show that during the Civil War Glasgow joined Company I, 4th Virginia Infantry in April, 1862, serving on detached duty in Staunton until being discharged in July. In 1863, he served as a captain leading the South River Home Guard.
On May 12, 1874, Glasgow married Laura B. Mackey (1853-1909), daughter of Henry and Nancy Hamilton Mackey, and the couple would have six children: Alexander M., John Henry ("Harry"), Elizabeth V., Lucy G., Mary T., and Otelia M. Glasgow. Alexander M. Glasgow died on August 4, 1894, and was buried in Stonewall Jackson Memorial Cemetery, Lexington, Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of the Glasgow family of Rockbridge County, Virginia. The collection includes such materials as correspondence and financial/legal documents relating to farmer and businessman Alexander McNutt Glasgow; his parents, John and Martha McNutt Glasgow; wife Laura Mackey Glasgow; son John Henry "Harry" Glasgow; other children; and related families.
Alexander Glasgow's papers comprise the majority of the collection. The papers relate largely to business matters, personal finances, and several estates for which Glasgow acted as administrator (including that of his uncle, Anderson McNutt, of Mississippi). Also among Glasgow's papers are folders relating to Ben Salem Church and a Richmond and Alleghany Railroad siding and crossing at South River. A folder devoted to school is largely composed of secondary school and Washington and Lee University grade reports for Glasgow's children.
The papers of Glasgow's parents and wife consist entirely of receipts and account statements. The papers of son J. "Harry" Glasgow, too, hold such materials but also contain several pieces of correspondence, including two letters from his brother, Alexander M. Glasgow, Jr. Among the other relatives represented are the Alexander N. Bell and Lucius Desha families, the collection holding small selections of correspondence and other papers from each family. The collection also holds financial papers of Edward I. Jones (and his business, Buena Vista Plumbing and House-Heating Company) and John Kerr. Folders of general correspondence and financial/legal documents contain a few materials relating to other family members and other, unrelated (sometimes unidentified) individuals. A folder of printed materials and mementos at the end of the collection contains, among other things, a handbill with instructions for water-proof leather blacking, a handwritten recipe for green tomato pickles, a business card for veterinarian E. E. Terry, and a lock of hair.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by alphabetically by name of family member with which materials are associated, followed by materials associated with individuals outside the immediate family or unidentified.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Geographical Names:
Rockbridge County (Va.)
Contents List
- Alexander M. Glasgow correspondence, 1871-1893, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Alexander M. Glasgow receipts and account statements, 1840-1893, n.d., [5 folders] (Box-folder 1-2)
- Alexander M. Glasgow checks, 1870-1888, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Alexander M. Glasgow promissory notes, 1870-1893, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Alexander M. Glasgow general financial documents, 1847-1893, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Alexander M. Glasgow legal documents, 1868-1893, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Ben Salem Presbyterian Church, 1870-1892 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Anderson McNutt estate, 1871-1885 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Richmond and Alleghany Railroad siding / crossing, 1882 (Box-folder 1-9)
- School, 1867-1896, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- John Glasgow papers, 1823-1830 (Box-folder 1-11)
- John Henry "Harry" Glasgow papers, 1891-1902, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Laura Glasgow papers, 1880-1899 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Martha Glasgow papers, 1825-1856, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Bell family papers, 1883-1895, n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Desha family papers, 1851-1903 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Edward I. Jones / Buena Vista Plumbing and House-Heating Company papers, 1887-1898 (Box-folder 2-5)
- John Kerr, 1835-1869 (Box-folder 2-6)
- General correspondence, 1882-1902, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Bessie Glasgow to "Miss Laura," 1899, n.d., [2 items]
  - Backus Water Motor Company to Unidentified, n.d., [fragment]
  - Lucy Effinger to "Mr. Glasgow," n.d., [2 items]
  - A. [Ann] Louisa Hickman to "very dear cousin," n.d.
  - Karn and Hickson to D. C. Irwin, 1882
  - V. C. Swinford to Unidentified, 1902
  - Jas. P. Woods to unidentified, n.d., [fragment]
  - Unidentified to Dr. Strain, 1893, [fragment?]
- General financial and legal documents, 1838-1893, n.d. (Box-folder 2-8)
- Printed material and mementos, 1893-1908, n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)